Dougal Dobie

I am an OzGrav Postdoctoral Research Fellow at the University of Sydney working in gravitational wave follow-up, with an interest in radio transients and high-energy astrophysics. I'm also interested in multi-wavelength transients science, data science and machine learning.

Employment

OzGrav Postdoctoral Research Fellow Radio Follow-up of Gravitational Wave Events	University of Sydney 2024-present
OzGrav Postdoctoral Research Fellow	Swinburne
Multi-wavelength Follow-up of Gravitational Wave Events	2020–2024

Education

Doctor of Philosophy (Science)	University of Sydney
Thesis title: Radio follow-up of gravitational wave events.	2017–2021
Supervisors: Prof. Tara Murphy, Prof. Richard Hunstead, Dr. Keith Bannister.	

Bachelor of Science (Advanced) (Honours Class I)
Physics (major), Applied Mathematics and Computational Science

University of Sydney

2013-2016

Refereed Publications

I am first author of 8 refereed publications, and my paper on the radio follow-up of GW170817 was awarded the University of Sydney Faculty of Science Postgraduate Research Prize for Outstanding Academic Achievement. I am also a co-author of 32 other papers published in a range of journals including *Nature* and *Science*. My h-index is 22, with over 6,000 total citations (>250 citations for first author papers).

Awards and Commendations

Swinburne Academic Promotion (Level A to Level B)	2022
University of Sydney Postgraduate Research Prize for Outstanding PhD Thesis (Science)	2022
University of Sydney School of Physics Prize for The Best PhD Thesis	2021
Australian Institute of Physics (NSW Branch) Award for Postgraduate Excellence in Physics	2019
USyd Faculty of Science Postgraduate Research Prize for Outstanding Academic Achievement	2019

Successful Telescope Proposals

I have been awarded over 1000 hours of ATCA time as Principle Investigator, including 750 hours for follow-up of gravitational wave events. I am co-Investigator on multiple other standard and target-of-opportunity ATCA proposals, totalling several hundred hours of observing time.

I have been awarded time as Principal Investigator with the Australian Square Kilometre Array Pathfinder (42 h), Parkes (66 h), the Long Baseline Array (40 h), the Karl G. Jansky Very Large Array (11 h), the Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope (20 h), MeerKAT (14.5 h), Keck (1 night), Gemini (11 h) and Swift (5.5 ks).

I am also a co-I of several proposals on the Australian Square Kilometre Array Pathfinder (130 h), the Karl G. Jansky Very Large Array (280 h), the Dark Energy Camera (11 nights), and the Murchison Widefield Array (3 h),

I am Project Scientist of the Variables And Slow Transients Survey which has been allocated over 2000 hours on the Australian Square Kilometre Array Pathfinder.

Professional Activities

Professional Activities	
Steering Committee member Astronomical Society of Australia - Time Domain Astronomy Chapter	2023–present
Co-Chair: Multi-Messenger Observations Program ARC Centre of Excellence for Gravitational Wave Astrophysics	2022–present
Project Scientist ASKAP Variables And Slow Transients Survey	2022–present
Early Career Researcher Committee ARC Centre of Excellence for Gravitational Wave Astrophysics	2021-present
Colloquium Organiser Swinburne Centre for Astrophysics and Supercomputing	2021–2023
Reviewer Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope Time Allocation Committee	2024–present
Reviewer Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, The Astrophysical Journal	2020–present
ATCA Duty Astronomer Assist observers using the Australia Telescope Compact Array	2017–2020
Australia Telescope User Committee Representative Liase between the telescope user community and ATNF Director	2018–2019

Invited Talks	
Exploring the Dynamic Radio Sky with ASKAP Physics Seminar	University of Melbourne October 2023
Radio Follow-up of Gravitational Wave Events SPI-MAX Seminar	Oxford University June 2021
Radio Follow-up of Gravitational Wave Events Australia Telescope National Facility Colloquium	CSIRO March 2021
Radio Follow-up of Gravitational Wave Events International Centre for Radio Astronomy Research Colloquium	ICRAR-Curtin August 2020
Exploring the Universe with Gravity & Light The 5th Chinese SKA Summer School 2019	Shanghai Astronomical Observatory August 2019

Scholarships and Funding

Local Organising Committee Science At Low Frequencies IV

University of Sydney Postgraduate Research Support Scheme	2019
University of Sydney Merit Award	2017-2020
Research Training Program (RTP) Stipend Scholarship	2017-2020

2017

Teaching Experience

PhD Co-supervisor **Swinburne**

James Freeburn - "Deeper, Wider, Faster" 2022-Present

Swinburne CAS Winter Vacation Scholarship supervisor Callan Gately: Multiwavelength transients with ASKAP and ZTF 2022

Swinburne CAS Summer Vacation Scholarship supervisor

Lachlan Graham & Archie Fox: Radio transients with ASKAP

University of Sydney **Undergraduate Tutor** Lab tutor (2nd & 3rd Year Physics), Night Viewing guide (First Year Astronomy) 2016-2020

Teaching Assistant University of Sydney

OLET1618 - Data Driven Astronomy: Algorithms 2018-2020

Online Tutor Coursera

2017-2020 Coursera – Data Driven Astronomy

Shanghai Astronomical Observatory Lecturer The 5th Chinese SKA Summer School 2019 August 2019

Undergraduate Research Advisor University of Sydney

Pablo Bonilla Ataides - "Prospects for radio follow-up of BNS mergers" 2019

Workshop development **GROWTH Astronomy School**

Undegraduate workshop on radio data analysis December 2018, August 2019

Course Development University of Sydney

Material for Data Driven Astronomy online course 2016/17

Selected Public Outreach

Astronomy Educator Sydney Observatory

2016-2020 Educating school groups and the general public

Workshop Facilitator & Science Advisor **Galaxy Convention**

Promoting female innovation and entreupenership in STEM 5 December 2017

Mosman High School Science in a Lunchtime

17 November 2017 Q&A: Exploring the Hidden Universe & Careers in Astronomy

CAASTRO Astronomer in Residence Ayers Rock Resort

Educating the general public & promoting Australian astronomy August 2017

University of Sydney **Sydney Astrofest**

Interacting with the public and general logistics 2016, 2017

2021-22

Refereed Publications

First Author...

Dobie, D., Sluse, D., Murphy, T., et al. 2023a, Gaia GraL: Gaia DR2 Gravitational Lens Systems. VIII. A radio census of lensed systems, MNRAS (submitted), arXiv:2311.07836

Dobie, D., Pritchard, J., Wang, Y., et al. 2023b, Radio transients and variables in the tenth Deeper, Wider, Faster observing run, MNRAS, 519, 4684

Dobie, D., Stewart, A., Hotokezaka, K., et al. 2022, A comprehensive search for the radio counterpart of GW190814 with the Australian Square Kilometre Array Pathfinder, MNRAS, 510, 3794

Dobie, D., Murphy, T., Kaplan, D. L., et al. 2021, Radio afterglows from compact binary coalescences: prospects for next-generation telescopes, MNRAS, 505, 2647

Dobie, D., Kaplan, D. L., Hotokezaka, K., et al. 2020, Constraining properties of neutron star merger outflows with radio observations, MNRAS, 494, 2449

Dobie, D., Stewart, A., Murphy, T., et al. 2019b, An ASKAP Search for a Radio Counterpart to the First High-significance Neutron Star-Black Hole Merger LIGO/Virgo S190814bv, ApJ, 887, L13

Dobie, D., Murphy, T., Kaplan, D. L., et al. 2019a, An optimised gravitational wave follow-up strategy with the Australian Square Kilometre Array Pathfinder, PASA, 36, e019

Dobie, D., Kaplan, D. L., Murphy, T., et al. 2018, A Turnover in the Radio Light Curve of GW170817, ApJ, 858, L15

Co-authored.....

Anumarlapudi, A., Ehlke, A., Jones, M. L., et al. 2023, Characterizing Pulsars Detected in the Rapid ASKAP Continuum Survey, ApJ, 956, 28

Rose, K., Pritchard, J., Murphy, T., et al. 2023, Periodic Radio Emission from the T8 Dwarf WISE J062309.94-045624.6, ApJ, 951, L43

Ho, A. Y. Q., Perley, D. A., Gal-Yam, A., et al. 2023, A Search for Extragalactic Fast Blue Optical Transients in ZTF and the Rate of AT2018cow-like Transients, ApJ, 949, 120

Andreoni, I., Coughlin, M. W., Perley, D. A., et al. 2022, A very luminous jet from the disruption of a star by a massive black hole, *Nature*, 612, 430

Ho, A. Y. Q., Margalit, B., Bremer, M., et al. 2022, Luminous Millimeter, Radio, and X-Ray Emission from ZTF 20acigmel (AT 2020xnd), ApJ, 932, 116

Wang, Y., Murphy, T., Kaplan, D. L., et al. 2022, Discovery of PSR J0523-7125 as a Circularly Polarized Variable Radio Source in the Large Magellanic Cloud, ApJ, 930, 38

Connor, T., Stern, D., Krone-Martins, A., et al. 2022, Gaia GraL: Gaia DR2 Gravitational Lens Systems. VII. XMM-Newton Observations of Lensed Quasars, ApJ, 927, 45

Makhathini, S., Mooley, K. P., Brightman, M., et al. 2021, The Panchromatic Afterglow of GW170817: The Full Uniform Data Set, Modeling, Comparison with Previous Results, and Implications, ApJ, 922, 154

Stern, D., Djorgovski, S. G., Krone-Martins, A., et al. 2021, Gaia GraL: Gaia DR2 Gravitational Lens Systems. VI. Spectroscopic Confirmation and Modeling of Quadruply Imaged Lensed Quasars, ApJ, 921, 42

Murphy, T., Kaplan, D. L., Stewart, A. J., et al. 2021, The ASKAP Variables and Slow Transients (VAST) Pilot Survey, PASA, 38, e054

Wang, Z., Kaplan, D. L., Murphy, T., et al. 2021, Discovery of ASKAP J173608.2-321635 as a Highly Polarized Transient Point Source with the Australian SKA Pathfinder, ApJ, 920, 45

Leung, J. K., Murphy, T., Ghirlanda, G., et al. 2021, A search for radio afterglows from gamma-ray bursts with the Australian Square Kilometre Array Pathfinder, MNRAS, 503, 1847

Bhakta, D., Mooley, K. P., Corsi, A., et al. 2021, The JAGWAR Prowls LIGO/Virgo O3 Paper I: Radio Search of a Possible Multimessenger Counterpart of the Binary Black Hole Merger Candidate S191216ap, ApJ, 911, 77

Kasliwal, M. M., Anand, S., Ahumada, T., et al. 2020, Kilonova Luminosity Function Constraints Based on Zwicky Transient Facility Searches for 13 Neutron Star Merger Triggers during O3, ApJ, 905, 145

Wang, Z., Murphy, T., Kaplan, D. L., Bannister, K. W., & Dobie, D. 2020, The capability of the Australian Square Kilometre Array Pathfinder to detect prompt radio bursts from neutron star mergers, PASA, 37, e051

Horesh, A., Sfaradi, I., Ergon, M., et al. 2020, A Non-equipartition Shock Wave Traveling in a Dense Circumstellar Environment around SN 2020oi, ApJ, 903, 132

Ackley, K., Adya, V. B., Agrawal, P., et al. 2020, Neutron Star Extreme Matter Observatory: A kilohertz-band gravitational-wave detector in the global network, PASA, 37, e047

Andreoni, I., Goldstein, D. A., Kasliwal, M. M., et al. 2020, GROWTH on S190814bv: Deep Synoptic Limits on the Optical/Near-infrared Counterpart to a Neutron Star-Black Hole Merger, ApJ, 890, 131

Kaplan, D. L., Dai, S., Lenc, E., et al. 2019, Serendipitous Discovery of PSR J1431-6328 as a Highly Polarized Point Source with the Australian SKA Pathfinder, ApJ, 884, 96

Chatys, F. W., Bedding, T. R., Murphy, S. J., et al. 2019, The period-luminosity relation of red supergiants with Gaia DR2, MNRAS, 487, 4832

Ho, A. Y. Q., Phinney, E. S., Ravi, V., et al. 2019, AT2018cow: A Luminous Millimeter Transient, ApJ, 871, 73 Mooley, K. P., Frail, D. A., Dobie, D., et al. 2018b, A Strong Jet Signature in the Late-time Light Curve of GW170817, ApJ, 868, L11

Mooley, K. P., Nakar, E., Hotokezaka, K., et al. 2018a, A mildly relativistic wide-angle outflow in the neutron-star merger event GW170817, *Nature*, 554, 207

Andreoni, I., Ackley, K., Cooke, J., et al. 2017, Follow Up of GW170817 and Its Electromagnetic Counterpart by Australian-Led Observing Programmes, PASA, 34, e069

Kasliwal, M. M., Nakar, E., Singer, L. P., et al. 2017, Illuminating gravitational waves: A concordant picture of photons from a neutron star merger, *Science*, 358, 1559

Hallinan, G., Corsi, A., Mooley, K. P., et al. 2017, A radio counterpart to a neutron star merger, *Science*, 358, 1579

Abbott, B. P., Abbott, R., Abbott, T. D., et al. 2017, Multi-messenger Observations of a Binary Neutron Star Merger, ApJ, 848, L12

Murphy, T., Kaplan, D. L., Bell, M. E., et al. 2017, Low-Frequency Spectral Energy Distributions of Radio Pulsars Detected with the Murchison Widefield Array, PASA, 34, e020

Bell, M. E., Murphy, T., Johnston, S., et al. 2016, Time-domain and spectral properties of pulsars at 154 MHz, MNRAS, 461, 908